SURAJ RAI

Protfolio | LinkedIn | GitHub | Leetcode

Location: Indiranagar, Bangalore Email: surajraieng@gmail.com | Mobile:+91-8862854905

FULL STACK DEVELOPER

I am a highly skilled web developer with over one year of experience in HTML, CSS, JavaScript, and Node.js. My expertise includes working with popular frameworks such as **React and Express.js**. I have substantial experience with **REST APIs**, **MVC frameworks**, and a solid understanding of **MongoDB** for database management.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Languages : JavaScript, Java, HTML, CSS and DSA

Frameworks : React.js, Express, Node.js
Libraries : Redux, React Router

Databases : MongoDB, MySQL

Dev Tools : Visual Studio Code, Git

EXPERIENCE

Web DeveloperMarch 2023 – March 2024WebreateDehradun, Uttarakhand, India

- Designed and developed dynamic and responsive websites using React, Node.js, Express.js and mongodb
- Worked with **REST APIs** to retrieve and display data from databases
- Improved website performance and speed through optimization techniques by 55%

Frontend Developer Intern

Oct 2022 – Feb 2023 Bangalore, India

Assiste senior web developers in the design and development of websites using HTML, CSS, JavaScript, React

EDUCATION

Sharpener Tech

Motihari College of Engineering B.Tech in Electrical and Electronics Engineering	Motihari, Bihar, India Aug 2018 – Aug 2022
Jan Sahkari College	Ara, Bihar, India
Intermediate (Science Stream)	<i>March 2018</i>
M.D.J Public School	Ara, Bihar, India
Matriculation (10th Grade)	<i>March 2016</i>

PROJECTS

Expense-Tracker

React.js, Node.js, Express.js, MongoDB, Razorpay

Source Code

- Implemented a full-stack CRUD application with JWT authentication for secure user management.
- Integrated Razorpay for payment processing; upon successful payment, user role is upgraded to premium.
- Allowed premium users to download all expenses in Excel format for better financial management.
- Utilized **responsive design** to ensure compatibility across all devices.

Chat-App Node.js, Express, JavaScript, Git, React, MongoDB, WebSocket

Source Code

- Developed a full-stack Chat application for real-time chat functionality using the MERN stack
- Implemented WebSocket for real-time, bidirectional communication between clients and server.
- Utilized Cookies for secure user authentication and session management.

CERTIFICATIONS

- Certified Java programming in NPTEL
- HackerRank: Certified in javaScript
- · HackerRank: Certified in Node.js